[Music]
let a and b both be real numbers with a
greater than or equal to b and b greater
than or equal to zero consider a line
segment with length a
and then overlay a line segment of
length b like this
use half of the uncovered length of the
first segment a length of a minus b over
two
to create a circle with a radius of a
minus b over two
[Music]
the yellow line segment created here
connecting the end of the line segment
to the center of the circle has length a
plus b over 2.
draw a radius perpendicular to the line
segment and connect the endpoints of
this radius and the end of the extended
line segment
the resulting triangle is a right
triangle so we can use the pythagorean
theorem to determine that the hypotenuse
has a length of square root of a minus b
over 2 squared plus a plus b over two
squared which simplifies to the square
root of a squared plus b squared over
two
next draw the tangent line to the circle
that passes through the endpoint of the
extended line segment and draw a radius
to this point creating another right
triangle highlighted here
we again use the pythagorean theorem to
determine that the missing leg has a
length of square root of a plus b over 2
squared minus the quantity a minus b
over 2 squared which simplifies to the
square root of a times b
finally drop a perpendicular from the
tangent point on the circle to the
extended line segment
one of the newly created triangles in
the subdivision is similar to the
original triangle
we can see that they're similar because
they're both right triangles and they
share one of the other angles
using the similarity of these triangles
we can find that the leg labeled x
satisfies the equality x over the square
root of a times b equals the square root
of a times b over a plus b over two
we can solve for x to see that x is two
times a times b over a plus b
[Music]
working backward we see that two times a
times b divided by a plus b is the leg
of a right triangle with hypotenuse the
square root of a times b so two a b over
a plus b is less than or equal to the
square root of a times b but the square
root of a times b is the leg of a right
triangle with hypotenuse a plus b over
two so the square root of a times b is
less than or equal to a plus b over two
and then a plus b over two is a leg and
a right triangle with hypotenuse the
square root of a squared plus b squared
over two
so a plus b over two is less than or
equal to the square root of a squared
plus b squared over two
two a b over a plus b is the harmonic
mean
the square root of a times b is the
geometric mean and a plus b over 2 is
the arithmetic mean and the square root
of a squared plus b squared over 2 is
the root mean squared the resulting set
of inequalities is known as the mean
inequalities we note that we get
equality throughout if and only if a
equals b in this case the entire picture
collapses to a single line segment
representing all of the values
[Music]
you